This ties into something that you
mentioned your piece that I haven't
heard
anyone else talking about, but I'll give
the sentence as a cue. I don't think
you'll need it, but founders running
successful AI companies should all take
a cold hard look at exiting in the next
12 to 18 months, which might be a value
maximizing moment for outcomes. And you
sort of went back to
the dot-com bust and the sort of
survival rates and then breakout rates.
Could you just explain that sentence
sure and then also explain how you're
thinking about whether you think this
will be winners take all oligopoly, like
what type of dynamic you think emerges?
>> In terms of the precedent and that
doesn't mean it's going to happen here,
but if you look at every technology
cycle
90 95 99% of the companies in that cycle
go bust.
>> Mhm.
>> And that dates way back even to what was
high-tech 100 years ago, which was the
automotive industry. In Detroit dozens
of car companies and hundreds of
suppliers and it collapsed into a small
number of auto companies eventually. And
so this is not a story during the
internet cycle or bubble of the '90s
450 companies went public in '99. 450 or
so companies went public in the first
few months of of 2000.
And so that was 900 companies and say
another
500 or 1,000 went public in the couple
years before that. So you had somewhere
between 1,500 and 2,000 companies go
public.
Go public. So that means they kind of
made it.
>> Mhm.
>> And of those how many have survived? A
dozen? Maybe two dozen?
>> Yeah.
>> And so out of 2,000 companies 1,980
or so went under.
>> Mhm.
>> What form or another maybe they got
bought for a little bit.
And so there's no reason to think the AI
cycle will be any different. And every
cycle's like that. SaaS was like that.
Automobile was like that and crypto was
like that.
So most companies are not going to make
it. A handful will and we can talk about
those. And so if you're running an AI
company right now, you should ask
yourself what is the nature of the
durability of your company?
And are you one of that dozen or two
that are going to be really important 10
years from now?
Or is now a good moment for you to sell
because what you're doing will start to
get commoditized, or will be competed by
a lab, or will be something that the
market will shift, or the technology
will shift, and you'll become obsolete.
And there's a handful of companies that
will continue to be great. They should
never sell, they should never exit, they
should keep going.
But there's probably a lot of companies
that now or the next 12 to 18 months is
the best moment for them possible in
terms of value that they'll get for what
they're doing. And for every company
there's a value maximizing moment where
they hit their peak. And it's usually a
window. It's usually a you know, 6 12
months where what you're doing is
important enough, you're scaling enough,
everything's working before some
headwind hits you.
And sometimes it's very predictable that
that headwind is coming and you can see
it, and often you see it in the second
derivative of growth. Like, how fast are
you growing starts to plateau a little
bit, and you're either going to keep
going up or you should sell. And so,
that's really what that's meant to be.
I'm incredibly bullish around AI as you
can tell from the rest of the
conversation. And so it's lots about the
transformation that's happening overall
because of the technology.
And more that only a handful of
companies are going to continue to be
really important. And so, are you one of
them or not? If you're one of them, you
should never ever ever sell.
>> So, what are the characteristics of that
handful? The handful that have durable
advantage? Because you look back at
2000, it's like, man, what would you
have used to try to pick out Google and
Amazon?
>> Yeah.
>> And I'm not saying that's the best
comparator, but
within the
many just avalanche of AI companies
which are those that you think have
durable advantage? I mean, of course,
some of the name brand
labs come to mind. Maybe they become the
interface for everything else, who
knows. But how would you answer that in
terms of either shared characteristics
or actual names, what sets apart the
handful that you think
will make it?
>> I think the core labs will be around for
a while. So, that's OpenAI, Anthropic,
Google barring some accident or disaster
or some blow up, but it seems like
they're in a really durable spot. And to
your point on like market structure, I
wrote a Substack post, I don't know, 3
years ago or something predicting that
that would probably be an oligopoly
market and there'd be a handful and it'd
be aligned with the clouds. And that's
roughly kind of what happened. I mean,
there's Meta and there's xAI and there's
other players that may change this that
didn't exist when I wrote that post.
But it feels to me like in the short run
that's an oligopoly. Like there's no
reason for that to be a monopoly market
unless one of them pulls ahead so much
in capabilities that it just becomes a
default for everyone. And that could
happen, but so far it hasn't. And again,
this compute constraint may prevent that
in the short run or at least provide an
asymptote on it. As you move up the
stack and you see well, there's
different application companies, you
know, there's Harvey for legal, there's
a Bridge for health, there's Decagon and
Sierra for customer success, you know,
there's these different companies per
application, there's three or four
lenses that you can look at.
One is if the underlying model gets
better, does your product or service get
dramatically better for your customers
in a way that they still want to keep
using you?
Second, how deep and broad are you going
from a product perspective?
Are you building up multiple products?
Are they all integrated in a cohesive
whole? Is it really being built directly
into the processes in a company in a way
that it's hard to pull out?
Often the issue for companies
in adoption of AI isn't how good is the
AI, it's how much do I have to change
the workflows and the ways that my
people do things in order to adopt it.
It's about change management usually,
it's not about technology. And so, if
you've been able to embed yourself
enough into workflows and how people do
business and how they work and how
everything else kind of ties together,
that tends to be quite durable.
>> Mhm.
>> Are you capturing and storing and using
proprietary data? Sometimes that's
useful. I think data moats in general
are overstated,
but I think sometimes it can be actually
quite useful. Then that's usually the
system of record view of the world.
So, you know, there's a handful of
criteria around like will this thing be
long-term
defensible or not? And the application
level that's often one potential lens on
it.
>> Mhm. So, question if if people are
listening to this and they are in the
position of perhaps a founder who should
consider identifying their
kind of short period of maximum
valuation and perhaps hitting the
parachute in some way. What are the
options? Because I think of some of
these companies, I'm not going to name
them, but uh there are multiple
companies that have multi-billion dollar
valuations.
>> I see.
>> There seems to be, again, from a mostly
layperson perspective, i.e. me,
that that the labs
probably can build what they are
currently selling without too much
trouble. Do they aim to be acquired by a
lab, in which case there's sort of a
build versus buy decision for the lab
itself? Are they aiming for one of not
the OpenAIs or Anthropic's, but maybe
somebody who's trying to get more skin
in the game, like Amazon or fill in the
blank?
What are the exit options?
>> I think there's a lot of exit options.
And the thing that's crazy right now is
if you go back 10 or 15 years,
the biggest market cap in the world was
like 300 billion.
>> Mhm.
>> The biggest tech market cap was, I don't
know, 200-ish or something. I think the
biggest one at the time was
Exxon or somebody, like 15 years ago.
>> Mhm.
>> And over the last 10 or 15 years, what
happens is we suddenly ended up with
these multi-trillion dollar market caps,
which everybody thought was nuts at the
time, but things will probably only get
bigger. There'll probably be more
aggregation versus less into the biggest
winners.
And there's more and more companies who
have these market caps between, say, 100
billion and a few trillion.
>> Mhm.
>> In a way, this is unprecedented. And
that means there's enormous buying
power, because 1% of 3 trillion is 30
billion. Right? You can
do 1% and pay 30 billion dollars for
something, which is insane, right?
That's that's really unprecedented. And
that means that these really big
acquisitions can happen. For the
companies that I'm imagining, again, I
don't want to name names,
that may have seem to have a limited
lifespan, right? When I'm in these these
small group threads with friends of mine
who are often time, not always, but I'm
in a bunch of them and when they're
tech investors, very successful tech
investors, and I'm like, "Okay, these
five companies, you've got 10 chips. How
would you allocate your 10 chips?"
There's certain companies that
consistently get zero, even though
they're reasonably well known. Why would
one of the labs buy one of those?
>> Depends on what it is, and it may be a
lab, it may be one of the big tech
incumbents, an Apple, Amazon. Right.
Google's kind of both things. There's
Oracle, there's Samsung, there's
Tesla, there's SpaceX now in the market
doing things. There's a bunch of
different buyers of different types.
There's Snowflake and Databricks,
there's Stripe.
>> Mhm.
>> Coinbase if you're doing financial
service. There's just a ton of companies
that actually are quite large. That's
kind of the point. And so often you end
up selling to one of four things. You
can sell to one of the big labs or
hyperscalers or giant tech companies.
You can sell to somebody who cares a lot
about your vertical. So, for example, a
Thomson Reuters if you're doing legal or
accounting or things that are kind of
related to that.
>> Mhm.
>> I mean, I think actually one thing that
doesn't happen enough is merger of
competitors, particularly private
companies where you can do that. Because
ultimately, if your primary vector is
winning, and you're neck and neck with
somebody and you're competing on every
deal and you're destroying pricing for
each other, like, maybe it's better to
just merge. That actually was
x.com and PayPal in the '90s, right?
Elon Musk here, you know, we're running
different companies and they merged
because they said we're two people doing
this, why fight?
>> Yeah, or Uber Lyft way back in the day,
right? That might not have been a
merger, it might have been an
acquisition, but it's like
>> Yeah, and the rumor is that that almost
happened and then, you know, the Uber
side walked away from it.
>> Mhm.
>> But all the money that Uber spent on
fighting Lyft for all those years maybe
would have been better spent just buying
them. Maybe not. I don't know the exact
math.
>> Mhm.
>> But, often it actually does make sense
to say, "You know what? Like, we'll just
stop fighting it out and we'll just
combine
and just go win." Cuz if the primary
purpose is to win the market, you're
already fighting all these big
incumbents that already exist anyhow.
So, why why make it even harder?